https://youtu.be/IXXHH6ztsSA does over 1 minus x, which gives you
mhthanh tính 1 - x, cho ra
0.4, then it multiplies these three things together,
0.4, sau đó nó nhân 3 thứ này với nhau
giving 0.93.
cho ra 0.93
And then what it is all done with all of that,
Sau khi xong hết chỗ đó
it takes that 0.93, and then puts it back into x.
nó lấy 0.93 ghi lại vào x
And so this is just sort of emphasizing
Ví dụ này là để nhấn mạnh
how the right-hand side is computed to produce a value,
phần bên tay phải được tính toán ra một giá trị
then it is moved into the variable.
rồi giá trị này được chuyển vào biến
And that is why you can have x on both sides.
Và đó là lý do tại sao bạn có x ở cả 2 bên
Because this is like the old, and this is the new.
Bên này là giá trị cũ, bên này là giá trị mới
The old x participates in the calculation.
Giá trị cũ của x tham gia vào việc tính toán
And then when the calculation is done, it becomes the new x.
Sau khi việc tính toán hoàn tất, x nhận giá trị mới
I hope that makes sense.
Tôi hy vọng là nó dễ hiểu
So this on the right-hand side here is a numeric expression.
Phần bên tay phải này là một biểu thức số học
So we have a number of different operators.
Ta có một số toán tử khác nhau
Some of them are instinctive, intuitive, the plus
Một số thì trực quan, như là cộng
and the minus.
và trừ
The reason some of these are so weird is in really old days,
Một số thì trông khá kỳ cục là vì ngày xưa
we didn't have too many things on the keyboard.
ta không có đủ các phím cần thiết trên bàn phím
And a lot of programs are very mathematical.
Và rất nhiều chương trình thì lại xử lý tính toán rất nhiều
And so they figured out what was on the keyboard of the computer
Nên họ tìm xem có những gì trên bàn phím của máy tính
equipment of the day, and then they
thời đó, rồi họ
had to fake certain things.
làm giả một số thứ
So it turns out that plus and minus were on the keyboard.
Hoá ra là dấu + và - thì hồi đó có trên bàn phím
And so plus and minus are addition and subtraction
nên + và - là phép cộng và phép trừ
respectively.
theo thứ tự
There was no kind of times operator for multiplication.
Không có dấu x cho phép nhân
And dot was used for decimal point.
Dấu chấm được dùng khi ghi số thập phân
So they used asterisks for multiplication.
Dấu * được dùng cho phép nhân
So in computers, languages, nearly all of them,
Hầu hết các ngôn ngữ trong máy tính
they basically use a times for multiplication.
sử dụng dấu * cho phép nhân
Slash is used for division.
Dấu gạch chéo được dùng cho phép chia
So we say like 8/2, which is 8 divided by 2.
8/2 nghĩa là 8 chia cho 2
Raising something to the power, like 4 squared,
Luỹ thừa một số nào đó, ví dụ như 4 bình phương
that is double asterisk.
thì dùng 2 dấu sao
And then remainder is if you do a division that
Tính phần dư, nếu bạn thực hiện phép chia
gives you the remainder rather than divisor.
để nhận phần dư thay vì phần nguyên
So 8 over 2 is 4, remainder 0.
ví dụ như 8/2 là 4, dư 0
So the remainder is what you get with this particular operator.
Bạn nhận phần dư của phép chia khi dùng toán tử đặc biệt này
There's a few cool things that we
Có vài thứ hay ho
can do with remainder that we won't talk about right away.
ta có thể làm với phần dư, nhưng sẽ chưa nói ngay bây giờ
And so here's just a couple of sample expressions.
Đây là vài biểu thức ví dụ
Let's give me green, OK.
Cho tôi bút màu xanh lá
So again, I'm using a Python interpreter.
Tôi lại dùng một trình thông dịch Python
So this is just the prompt.
Đây là dấu nhắc
The chevrons are the prompt.
Các ký tự ">>>" chính là dấu nhắc
Create the variable xx, and assign it to 2.
Tạo biến xx và gán nó bằng 2
Retrieve the old value in an addition.
Lấy giá trị cũ đưa vào phép cộng
Then print it out and put it back into xx, so xx has 4.
Đưa kết quả ngược lại vào xx và in ra, nên xx là 4
yy, this is a multiplication.
Biến yy. Đây là 1 phép nhân
440 times 12 is 5,280.
440 nhân 12 bằng 5,280
yy over 1,000, this is little counterintuitive.
yy chia 1000. Chỗ này hơi khó hiểu
Because yy is an integer, it then
Vì yy là biến số nguyên
does it in a truncated division.
nên chỗ này là phép chia với kết quả bị cắt cụt
So 5,280 divided by 1,000 is 5.
5280 chia 1000 cho kết quả là 5
And so that's an integer division.
Đó là phép chia với số nguyên
We'll see in a second about floating point division.
Ta sẽ thấy phép chia với số thực ngay thôi
Now we take the variable jj and we set it to 23.
Giờ ta tạo biến jj và gán nó bằng 23
And now we're going to use the modulo or remainder
Ta sẽ dùng toán tử %
operator to say what is the remainder when
để tính phần dư
we divide this jj by 5.
khi lấy jj chia 5
And so if you think about this, we
Nếu bạn nghĩ về điều này
take old long division, 23 divided by 5, you end up
23 chia cho 5
with 4, and then remainder 3.
được 4, dư 3
The modulo operator, or the percent, or the remainder
Toán tử %
operator, gives us back this number.
cho ra kết quả này
And so that's why kk is 3.
Và đó là lý do tại sao kk là 3
It is the remainder of 23 when divided
Nó là phần dư của 23 khi chia
by 5 or the remainder of the division of 5 and 23.
cho 5, hay là phần dư của phép chia giữa 5 và 23
And the raising to the power 4 cubed is 4**3.
4 luỹ thừa 3 ghi là 4**3
And so that end up being 64.
kết quả là 64
So that's just operations.
Đó chỉ là về các phép toán
Now just like in algebra and mathematics,
Như trong môn đại số và toán học
we have rules about which operations happen first.
Ta có luật về việc các phép toán nào xảy ra trước
In general, things like the power
Nói chung, những thứ như luỹ thừa
happens before the multiplication and division,
xảy ra trước nhân và chia
and then the addition and subtraction happen.
rồi cộng và trừ xảy ra sau đó
So there are some rules when you're looking at an expression
Có vài luật khi bạn nhìn vào một biểu thức
and trying to calculate what its value is.
và cố gắng tính toán giá trị của nó
If you don't have parentheses, it follows these rules.
Nếu bạn không có các dấu ngoặc, ta theo các luật này
And so the rule that sort of trumps all the rules
Nhưng có một luật cao hơn tất cả các luật khác
is that parentheses are always respected.
là các dấu ngoặc luôn có độ ưu tiên cao nhất
So a lot of us just write these with parentheses in place, even
Đa số chúng ta dùng dấu ngoặc
sometimes, though, you don't need it.
mặc dù đôi khi không cần
Then after parentheses have been handled,
Sau khi các dấu ngoặc được xử lý
then it does exponentiation.
thì đến phép luỹ thừa
Then it does multiplication, division, and remainder.
rồi nó thực hiện phép nhân, chia, và tính phần dư
And then it does addition and subtraction.
sau đó là phép cộng và phép trừ
And then, all else being equal, it just works left to right.
Khi các phép toán có độ ưu tiên giống nhau, thì tính từ trái sang phải
So let's look through an example.
Hãy xem một ví dụ
So here is a calculation that is 1 plus 2 times 3
Tính 1 + 2**3 / 4*5
divided by 4 over 5.
1 + 2**3 / 4*5
And the question is what order does this happen?
Câu hỏi là việc tính toán diễn ra theo thứ tự nào?